這一次的大會的重點之一就是敬拜讚美
這是非常好的一個重點
我也看見參加敬拜會的弟兄姊妹們很整齊
我相信這不是偶然的
我們一天的程序是很忙很重
要參加這個敬拜會需要早起來
大家能夠參加出席
這代表大家內心的一件事
我們在末世的時候
靠近七十六
所預言更近的時候
我們想到七十六裡面一個特點就是歌唱
唱新歌
唱新歌在七十六裡面是舊書的歌的意思
但是我相信新的意思還有一個意思
有一個姊妹這樣說
這首是我唱了幾十年了
今天受感動好像是第一次唱
I've sung this hymn for many many years many many times
But today when I sing it as if I'm singing it for the first time
新歌就是從心裡唱的歌
New song is a song you sing with your heart
我們願意在敬拜上
華人的教會的復興
That in our singing our worship
The Chinese Church must be revived
我有一個預感
And I have a sense that you beforehand
華人教會下一次的復興
很可能是從敬拜的復興引發出來的
That the next revival of the Chinese Church may be ushered in by our worship
我發現已經有越來越多的華人教會
開始在敬拜讚美上注重
I feel that the American Chinese Church
is now placing emphasis in our worship
這是很合神心意的一件事
This is according to the heart of the Lord
我們在敬拜中的心情中
Letting go to the point that in worship we want to receive the Word of God
我們來到查經的第二個分題
We want to come to the second topic of this theme
跟隨基督的代價
The cost of following Christ
與主同死
That is to die with him
我們的主向自己死了
Our Lord has died to himself
我們和他同死
And we also want to die with him
沒有人願意死的
No one wants to die
死這個字有中文的寫法
兩部分合成
In the Chinese characters
the death has two parts
一部分是歹
好歹的歹表示不好
另外一部分是一把刀
很好的刀
On one hand is the badness
On the other hand is a knife
So the knife which is bad is killing us
死好像一把刀
沒有人歡喜
讓這把刀刺入自己的心
Death is like a dagger
The one to pierce to our heart
但是我們的主為我們死了
But then our Lord died for us
他為我們捨棄
He has denied himself for us
他為我們背十字架
上十字架
He borne our cross
And he was crucified on the cross
因此我們願意和他同行
And because of that we want to walk with him
因此我們願意和他同背十字架
We want to bear the cross together with him
我們背十字架
不但是因為主說來跟從我
Find跟從我的
要背起他自己的十字架來跟從我
We want to bear the cross together with Christ
Not only that he just called us
So that we can bear the cross and walk with him
我們願意背十字架
也是從心裡面對極度的愛
極度的捨棄
極度的背十字架的回應
But also it is because of the response
within our heart
that it is the calling of God
剛才我們唱的詩
我要一路一路隨主行
That's now the song
the hymn that we are just sung
Way by way I will follow the Lord
這首詩很特別
這個副歌重複好多次
This song is very special
because the chorus is repeated many times
而且每一次的重複
都是在那裡加重
加重這個意思
Every repetition to add meaning to the verse
我要隨主 隨主行一路
I want to follow and follow Christ Jesus
through the way
行全程 所有的人生的道路
Through the whole life way
我們可能要開始
但是不能持續
Maybe we will stop
But we cannot persist
我們開始願意背十字架的時候
可能是情緒化的一件事
Maybe emotionally in the beginning
We want to follow the Lord Christ
開始就同行一段路以後
Then we walk for a certain distance
我們發現原來是如此
We find it so difficult
這麼多的難處
So many difficulties
這麼重的十字架的重量
Such a heavy cross is put upon us
慢慢就退後了
Slowly we retreat
在唱這首詩的時候
不容易從心底下
全心全意的唱出來了
So as we sing this hymn
Maybe it's difficult for us to sing
from within our heart
我看見過一幅漫畫
I saw a cartoon
有兩邊
Two sides
兩部分
Two parts
一部分呢
就是一群的基督徒
走在一條路上
On one path
there is a group of Christians
walking on the path
他們一面走一面唱
中華我心愛你
現在愛你
永遠愛你
And they sing
Along the way they say
Lord we love you now
We love you forever
後來他們來到一個十字路口
But later on
they come to a crossroad
有兩條路
Two way
有的人走這邊的路
Some will turn this way
那個路上寫著一個名字
愛世界的路
And it is written
The way to love the world
這一部分的基督徒
走愛世界的路
但是還在那裡唱
中華我心愛你
現在愛你
永遠愛你
And this group of Christians
they follow the way of the world
say that
and also sing that
Lord we love you now
We love you forever
另外一條路
On the other way
愛主的路
The way to love the Lord
一些弟兄姊妹
要走在這條路上
不過是少數
A group of Christians
also walk this way
but the rest cares
他們也繼續地唱
中華我心愛你
現在愛你
永遠愛你
They also continue to sing
Lord we love you with our heart
Now and forever more
這另外一邊
And on the other hand
也是一堆的基督徒
Also another group of Christians
走一條路
And they walk away
他們一邊走一邊唱
十字架
永是我的榮耀
And they sing that
In the cross, in the cross
Forever it is my glory
他們來到十字路口
And they come out of this junction
兩條路
Two ways
走在這邊的路上的人
They who walk this way
他們的景象上
戴了個十字架
On the next hand
was hung a cross
另外一條路的人
And the other way
他們的背上
背了十字架
But at the back
they bore a cross
他們都在那兒唱
十字架 十字架
永是我的榮耀
Where they sing
In the cross, in the cross
Forever it is my glory
但是他們和十字架的關係不同
But their relationship
with the cross is different
一個是裝飾品
One is as an ornament
肯戴十字架裝飾的人
我也很佩服他們
Well, I admire those
who can put up a cross
and be an ornament
這是以十字架為榮
Yes, you are
You feel glorious
because of this cross
This is an ender
Yes, it's something to be admirable
但是那些背十字架的人
更是蒙恩了
But he who bears a cross
is even more blessed
在那個圖畫裡面
有一個嬰兒
And there was a shadow
in the cartoon
基督 Christ
也背著他的十字架
He also bore his own cross
走在這一隊的前頭
And was leading in the whole group
我們跟著背十字架的族
一路 一路走下去
We were following Christ
who bore the cross
We and step by step
we walked with him
如果與主同死
與主兩個字拿掉
If we were to die with Christ
If we remove this word with
單純死
Just to say dying
我們都不要
We do not want
沒有一個人歡喜死
No one likes to die
沒有一個人歡喜向自己死
No one wants to die to himself
但是
有同主兩個字的時候
把背十字架的字
with Christ
一切都改觀了
Everything changed
這是主的路
This is the way of the Lord
榮耀的主
A glorious Christ
偉大的主
And also the mighty God
荒唐的主
The creator
最高的主
The almighty and highest God
他願意為我們兩個人死
For our sake
He died
讓我們的內心的響應
So I want to respond to him
我們說
We say Lord
你既然為我死
That you have died for me
我願意與你同死
And I want to die with you
我們裡面有了力量
We have strength within
我們捨棄一點的時候
When we die to ourselves
我們有喜樂
We have joy
我也相信
那個捨棄的喜樂
就是嫉妒心裡的喜樂
And I truly believe
that the joy of self-denial
is the joy of Christ
這個喜樂就是我們的力量
And that is the strength of us
我們的主
上十字架的時候
On the road when he walked up to the cross
他有喜樂
He has joy
他看見前面的喜樂
He saw the joy set before him
他就忍受困難
And he bared all the suffering
他眼睜睜看著十字架的時候
He despised all the shame of the cross
然後坐在神的右邊
And he sat down on the right hand side of God
他奔走這條路的時候
When he walked this way
他的喜樂是什麼
What is joy
就是這麼多的人因他的救
There are so many people through him are saved
我們奔走這條路的時候
喜樂是什麼
When we run this way
Where is our joy
就是我們的主
他這樣的愛我們
That is our Lord loves us so much
求聖靈
把神的愛交換在我們心裡
Pray that the Holy Spirit will pour the love of God upon our heart
只有在一個交換的狀態之中
我們才能歡歡喜喜地跟從主一路
一路到底
It is only in this state of anointing and pouring
Then we can follow the Christ to the end
有一節
有七節非常寶貴的聖經
A few very precious verses from the Bible
1 Peter 2
Philippians 2
第五節到第十一節
Verses 5 to 11
我要請大家安靜地讀一次
I want you to read it silently
一分鐘
One minute
我們每個人來自己讀
在心裡讀
Read to ourself in our heart
1 Peter 2
第五節到第十一節
Philippians 2
Verses 5 to 11
這是聖經裡面最寶貴的經文之一
This is one of the most precious passages in the Bible
把耶穌基督的形象
為我們描繪出來
That is painted the image of Christ before us
在這裡我們看見基督的心
Here we can see the mind of Christ
也是基督的行動
And also his action
把他的心發出來行動
The action that emitted from his mind
在這裡保羅說
我們要基督這樣的心為我們的心
And Paul said
You must have the mind of Christ as your mind
我們也以基督這樣的行動
做我們的行動
And have this action of Jesus Christ as your action
這是一條路
This is the way
基督教的信仰是一條路
Christianity is a way
跟從主的路
And the way to follow Christ
與主同死同活同得榮耀的路
That is to die together with him
Resurrect together with him
And also to glorify together with him
在世俗時代
In the time of the apostles
基督教的信仰有一個特別的名稱
That is a special name for the Christian belief
使徒行傳第九章第二節Act of the Night
Verse 2 says
凡信奉這道的人
這個道字的原文是道路
He who believes in this way in the original language
道路
Way
基督的信仰是一條道路
It's a way in Christianity
不是理論
Not a theory
不是觀念
Not a concept
那是一條路
But a way
我們合作同行到底的路
Then you want to work this way together with Christ Jesus
我們一起做的心
為心
一起做的路
為我們的路
With Christ's mind as our mind
With Christ's way as our way
我們在這裡看見主是怎麼樣的
Here we see what Christ is
他捨棄一切
He denied everything
放下一切
He gave up everything
他向自己死
He died to himself
他降妃
He humbled himself
當他這樣做的時候
When he did such
就是我們升高
It is then that we are raised
和我們交換了
And it's an exchange with us
他向下去
He descended
但我們向上去
We ascended
這樣一個交換
在這一季節裡面
這個意義非常明顯
Such an exchange in these few verses is clearly depicted
他向下我們向上
Then he decreased and we increased
但是不停止在這裡
Not only stopping at this place
我們向上以後
When he ascended
然後又合足一同降妃
Then together with Christ
we want to humble ourselves
有人就停止在
一同降妃
我身上就在那個聖經那裡停下了
But there are people
They say that Christ Jesus
descended and we ascended
They want to stop at that extension
那是半途
That is only half way
這個半途而廢
Do not give up half way
我們上上去以後
As we have been lifted up
他要和基督一同降妃
Together with Christ Jesus
We want to humble ourselves
這就是合足同行
This is the walk with Jesus Christ
所以開始是相反而行
走上下我們向上
In the beginning it was Christ Jesus
who would humble himself
and we are lifted up
It is the opposite way
後來是同行了
一起降妃向下
But later on it was the same way that we walk
We want to humble ourselves together
你看出在這裡向下一連七步
七步向下向下降妃降妃
一直到死在死者的架上
You see that Christ took a way of sliding
descending and humbling and humbling and humbling
這是我們的道路
This is our way
我們要看一看
怎麼樣走這條路
We want to see how our Christ walk this way
怎麼樣和我們交換
How did he exchange with us
然後我們看怎麼樣合足同行
and how we can walk together
with the Lord Jesus Christ
我們首先注意
First we want to pay attention to verse 6
他本有神的形象
不與自己與神同等於強奪的
Although in the form of God
we do not count equality with God
a thing to be grasped
我們注意強奪的三個字
to be grasped
意思就是說
把他當作權力緊緊地抓住
that is taking as a right
and then you want to hold it very tightly
不肯放棄
You do not want to give up
我們就剛剛相反
But our Christ is different in the reverse
他與神同等
He was equal with God
超越一切
transcend everything
這樣的一位主耶穌
Such a Christ
他不將他應得的權力
榮耀地位
當作不可放棄的特權
He does not count this as a right
equality with God
glory with God
something that he cannot give up
他放下他應有的權力
He denied
He gave up all the rights that he should have
這是起點
This is the beginning point
如果我們要合作同行
If we want to work together with Christ
我們必須有這個觀念
We must have this ideal
我們願意放棄我們認為應有的權力
We want to give up the right we deem as ours
凡是左手用的人
He who is used by God
都用這個心態
He must have this kind of mind
和從一同放下
我們原來要抓住的
Together with Christ
we want to denounce the thing that we have together
教會裡面有許多的問題
There are many problems in the church
因為要抓住特權
It is because we want to hold our rights very tightly
這是我的權利
This is my right
應得的權利
合理的權利
The reason for right
不可放棄
We cannot deny
抓住 緊緊地抓住
Hold it and hold it tightly
每一個人都這樣抓住的時候
Everybody holds to their right
每一個人的兩隻手都是這樣的
And this is the fist that we hold
不會伸出去幫助別人
We cannot stretch out and help others
不會給予
We cannot give
不會捨棄
We cannot deny ourselves
不會放下
We cannot put down ourselves
那是合作非道而屈
Then it is a different way we run with the Lord
放下權利
But to deny our rights
我們歡歡喜喜地合著一同做這件事
We rejoice when we do this thing together with Christ
感謝著
Praise the Lord
我們把這個權利放下
As we have given up this right
結果我們合作一起升高了
Then we ascended together with Christ
我們合作一同做王了
We are together with Him as King
將來合作一同做王的人
And He who reigns together with Christ in the future
會面的上次的人
He who received the crown
都是那些把權利放下的人
Are those who deny their right
結果抓住權利的人
He who holds the right
最後抓住的是什麼
Finally what do they hold on to
空的
Emptiness
最後是失望
Disappointment
最後是宣誓
And also our loss
感謝主
Praise the Lord
這是主的路
This is the way of the Lord
他放下的比我們放下的太多
What he has given up
Is very much more than what we can give up
最近
Recently
在美國
在美國的弟兄
There was an American brother
美國人的弟兄
An American brother
23歲
23 years old
在耶魯大學
Yale University
得到他的PhD
He got his PhD from Yale University
平常大學畢業以後
在這PhD要好多年
Usually it takes a long time
for him to get a PhD
他23歲
23 years old
He got his PhD
天才一類的人
He belongs to the party
He comes out like that
When the calling of the Lord
comes to him
叫他去宣教室
Want him to be a missionary
要接受說服
He submit to himself
要到阿根廷去
He want to go to Argentina
開始訓練
He began to be trained
別人問他
Someone asked him
你去到阿根廷
不覺得孤單嗎
Do you not feel lonely
to go to Argentina
他這樣回答
And he replied
你走和我一起去
怎麼會孤單
When the Lord is going together with me
how can I feel lonely
別人說你前途這麼燦爛
你這樣放下
是很大的損失
And the people said
your future is so bright
you want to give up this
such a great sacrifice you are making
他說
最高的主來到世界
他放下的比我放下的多得多了
Or the highest lord who come to the world
what he has denied
much much more than what I did
這麼一個相反的情況
And there is a reverse phenomenon in the state
這方面物質主義非常的流行氾濫
On the one hand
it is very popular with materialism
受社會分歧的影響
在青年的中間非常地強
The influence of this among the young people
is so strong
在這樣的情況下
It is in this circumstance
can we all understand
the people who want to sacrifice themselves
people who want to love the Lord
can we all understand
超越物質主義
can people transcend materialism
can we all understand
can people want to become a missionary
And you have done a good job
There is a big question
但是感謝主
But where is the Lord
Certain things are going wrong
The Holy Spirit is working
主教的愛沒有改變
The love of the cross has never changed
神的愛的激勵也沒有改變
Because the constraint of the love of the cross never changed
還是繼續有不少的青年
在那樣的環境跟長大的青年
把自己完全地奉獻
Continue young people grow up in a certain environment
continue to dedicate themselves to the Lord
當你看見第二個弟兄的時候
你有什麼感受
When you see such a brother
how would you feel
感謝主
Praise the Lord
十字架不改變
The cross never changed
我們的錯不改變
Our Lord never changed
許多愛他的人也不改變
The many people who love the Lord also never changed
許多超越潮流的人
Those who transcend the tides
許多得勝者
And those victorious people
我是的時候
In the last days
最難得勝的時候
The most difficult days in the victorious days
最難跟從主的時候
The most difficult days to follow Christ
還是有許多的人
愛主奉獻自己
跟從主
But they should reject
But yet there are many people
who want to love the Lord
who want to follow God
who want to carry the cross
我們真是要敬拜主
We want to worship our Lord
放棄權利
To deny your rights
主是如此
保羅也是如此
Paul is such
And also Christ is such
在格林多前書第九章
1 Corinthians 9
我們看見保羅放下了三樣的權利
We see the three rights that Paul has given up
都是不容易放棄的
They are not easy rights to give up
第一
放棄結婚的權利
The right of marriage
誰願意放棄這個權利
Who want to deny these rights
我在抗戰期間
In during the wars
在內地好些地方
也不算漂流了
總是受了
但是總是受了戰爭影響
不斷地遷移
In the inland
we have to move a lot because of war
我和好些內地會有接觸
I have contact with all the missionaries
看見一些內地會的宣教士
And seeing the missionary of China in the mission
他們中間的女宣教士比例很高
Especially there is a great proportion of women missionary
而且在他們中間不結婚的佔大多數
But among the majority do not get married
我看見他們很喜樂地工作
I see that they work with joy
全心全意地工作
They wholeheartedly work
把中國人打成一片那樣的工作
And they mingle and work together with the Chinese
每次看見他們我都感動
Every time when I see them
I was touched
沒有自己的家
They don't have their own home
Not their own home
但是教會弟兄姊妹是他們的大家族
But the church transistor is the big home
神放在人的天性裏面
母性裏面的那個家的愛
他們把它擴大了
在基督的家裏他們是否
The maternal love that God has put in them
they enlarge it so they will serve in the church
他們放棄了結婚的權利
They deny their right to marriage
巴羅也是這樣
Paul also is such
巴羅在那一章裏頭
臨前九章裏頭
Paul in 1 Corinthians 9
他七次提到權名兩個字
Seven times he talked about right or authority
權名就是權利
Authority or right
但是我既沒有這個權利
既沒有這個權利
沒有這個權利
沒有這個權利嗎
Isn't it that I have this right
that right and that right
七次提到權利
Seven times he mentioned about rights
又兩次提到自由
And two times he mentioned about freedom
但是我是自由的
I'm free
我是自由的
另外兩次
甘心
He was willing
I'm willing
這兩個字把問題都解決
This two words have solved all the problems
他甘心放下所有的權利
He was willing to deny all his rights
他甘心放下他一切一切的責任
He was willing to deny all his responsibilities
放下他完全的自由
And to deny his freedom
甘心放下
Willing
Willing to deny
獻給無名的傳道者
And dedicated to the anonymous preacher
我用自己的手
With my hand
放下了自由
I denounce my right
更大膽的取了另外的自由
And also I pick up a greater right
就是不自由的自由
That is the freedom in no freedom
把自己完全奉獻給主的自由
That is the freedom to dedicate yourself
and to be enslaved by Christ
放下自己的自由
The rights are the freedom to deny yourself
這是一個超越的自由
This is the right
This is the freedom to transcend all freedom
這是保羅氏的自由
This is the Pauline freedom
這是耶穌基督的自由
And it's the crystal freedom
在這個不自由裡頭
就有自由的真意義
That in this no freedom
He enjoys the true meaning of freedom
我們看基督
We see freedom
我們說基督是神所以能這樣
That we see that Christ because he's God
He can do such
So he can follow
As in Paul
我們怎麼說呢
What do we say
原來一個人也可以這樣
Oh a man also can do that
不但基督是這樣
Not only Christ such
一個完全奉獻的人也可以這樣
Or one who is totally dedicated also can be such
你我都可以走這條路
You and I can walk this way
感謝主
Praise the Lord
在婦女寺裡面
In the church
Which is the name of our law
There's not only one Paul
There's only one Paul
If there's only one Paul in China
That is beautiful
感謝主
But praise the Lord
千萬的保羅
The thousand and thousand Paul
千萬放下自己
放下權力
跟從主的人
Thousand and thousand who deny themselves
And deny their rights
And to follow Christ
我相信持續奉用十四萬四千這個數字
I代表這些人
I truly believe that 144,000 in Revelation
Represent this kind of people
The sinner
Those are victorious
這句話來形容他們
There's a word to describe them
無論高陽往哪裡去
他們都跟隨他
No matter where the lamb goes
They will follow
這句話讓我相信
And I believe
這些人是否僅僅跟從主的人
所以是得勝的人
Are those who follow Christ very closely
And that's why they are victorious
不是一個人
Not one person
十四萬四千
But 144,000
也不是十四萬四千
Not 144,000
也不是一個象徵
這個完全的數字
Because there's a figurative
Perfect number
感謝主
Praise the Lord
虛虛弱弱的人
Many many people
被嫉妒賴及利
They are constrained by the love of God
They are filled with the love of God
在那個被交換的狀態之下
這樣的依然決然
而且持續地跟從主到底
They are in a state of anointment
Determinately
Consistently
They want to follow God
放下了一切都養生的權利
And also deny the right of earning a living
Through the preaching
歡樂的工作有兩個階段
Past work has two stages
第一階段他是製造帳篷
The first phase was tent making
他自己來維持自己的生活
He undertakes the tent making
So that he can sustain himself
第二個時期
The second phase
他接受了教會的支持
He receives the support from the church
全時間地來傳福音
And full time he preaches the gospel
他是在職侍奉的一個榜樣
So we see that he is an example for tent makers
他是全職侍奉的榜樣
But also an example for those full time workers
一個人給我們兩方面的榜樣真是難得
One who has examples from both sides
無論在職侍奉
No matter tent making
無論全職侍奉
We are full time workers
我們都是跟從主耶穌
We are all following Christ
走主所走過的路
而且一路一路隨著而行
Walking the way Christ used to tread
And following closely behind him
Follow 放下自由的權利
Paul denied his right of freedom
甘心做僕人
And he wanted to be a servant
他對格林多的弟兄子們說
He told the brothers and sisters
in the Corinthian church
我因為耶穌基督的緣故
做你們的僕人
For the sake of Christ
I am your servant
波羅是基督的僕人
Paul is the servant of God
也是人的僕人
And also is the servant of man
有人說我只是基督的僕人
Someone said I am only the servant of Christ
我不是任何人的僕人
I am not everybody's servant
我想不合聖經
This is not biblical
波羅是為了基督做人的僕人
Paul for the sake of Christ
He become the slave and the servant of man
一個不肯做人不仁的人
不可能做基督的僕人
One who is not willing to become
the servant of man
cannot become the servant of Christ
我們藉著做人的僕人
來做基督的僕人
It is through becoming the servant of man
to become the servant of Christ
二一一二不能分開
It is two but one but one and yet two
感謝主
Praise the Lord
原諒我們是自由的
Actually we are free
為了基督的原因
But for the sake of Christ
我們做僕人
We become servants
做眾人的僕人
Servant of all people
結果
我們合作一同做王
We are together with Christ
reigning together with Him as King
我們看見基督
他舍己
We see that Christ Jesus
giving up Himself
He cheated
Verse 7
翻到虛己
And also He emptied Himself
humble Himself
他把自己放下
Then He denied His own self
倒空自己
empty Himself
這個包括了什麼
What does it include
舍己
That when you deny yourself
包括了什麼
What does it include
包括替我們成為貧窮
And becoming poor for our sake
包括什麼
What does it include
放下神的兒子
人的兒子的地位
做人的兒子
And to get out of the status
of being the Son of God
and become the Son of Man
他和我們交換了
And He exchanged with us
他原來是神的兒子
He was actually the Son of God
但是他倒沉入神
By the way becoming flesh
生在律法之下
And born under the law
做人的兒子
And become the Son of Man
為了叫我們成為神的兒子
So they become the children of God
神的兒子成為人的兒子
叫人子成為神子
The Son of God becoming the Man
The Son of Man
So that the Son of Man
become the children of God
加拿大書第四章
第四節五節六節
Galatians 2.2.4.5.6
感謝主
這個交換太寶貴
Such a pressure is extreme
神的兒子成為人
The Son of God becoming Man
使我們這些信眾的人成為神的兒子
So that we who believe in God
also become the children of God
不能有兒子的靈魂
Not only we have a position
to be the children of God
換句話說
不能有兒子的地位
Not only we have a status
to become the children of God
而且有兒子的靈進到我們裡面
But also the spirit of the Son
coming and dwell within us
不能有兒子的心
So that my oppressed
能夠呼叫阿爸父
So that we can call him Abba Father
不能如此
Not only so
我們還有兒子的形象
We also have the image
of the Son of God
希伯來書二章十節
Hebrews 2.2.10
神的兒子來
The Son of God come
到世上
To the world
結果帶著許多的兒子進入榮耀
And bringing many into glory
這是神的計劃
This is the plan of God
他的徒兄子來
Then his only son came
帶許多人成為神的兒子
Bringing many people
to become the children of God
有兒子的地位
With the position of the children of God
兒子的生命
And with the life
兒子的形象
With the image of the Son of God
然後和這位兒子耶穌基督
一起進永遠的榮耀裡面去
And together we cry with the Son of God
going and entering into glory
奇妙的作為
Such a wonderful act of God
奇妙的救恩
Such a marvelous salvation
我們有兒子的形象
We have the image of the Son of God
因為神的兒子成了人的形象
Because the Son of God
take the form of humankind
他替我們成為貧窮
He become poor on our behalf
格林圖後書第九章
也更講得很清楚
Second Corinthians chapter 9
also pointed out very clearly
他本來富足
That he was rich actually
替我們成了貧窮
For our sake he became poor
他讓我們成為富足
So that we become rich
也這是何等的奇妙一件事
Such a marvelous task indeed it is
我記得第一次讀
C.T. Stubb的傳記的時候
First time when I read the biography of Stubb
心裡受很深的感動
I was so deeply touched
他是劍橋七傑之一
He was one of the Cambridge Seven
他到中國來做宣教士
When he came to China to become a missionary
後來又到印度做宣教士
And then later to become a missionary in India
後來到非洲做宣教士
And then to Africa
在非洲的時候成立了
這個環球婦孕輔導會
In Africa he established a trans world evangelist
那個Michel他們叫Weck
I'm sorry Weck
EC Worldwide Evangelistic Crusade
他非洲大大的使用
He was very greatly used by God
這份傳記一打開
And this biography as I open it
第一頁的照片是什麼
What is the first picture that appears
就是他住在倫敦的時候的住者
That was his house in London
像個王宮一樣那麼漂亮
Palace
第二頁
And the second page
他在非洲做宣教士的時候住的茅屋
And this is a small hut that he stayed when he was in Africa
下面一句話
And what was written there
希伯來書第二章二十七節
Hebrews chapter 2 verse 27 and 28
他看為基督受的領入
比埃及一切的寶財寶更寶貴
That he deemed the suffering for the Lord
Christ is precious in all the treasures of Egypt
他方前原來最舒適的生活
為了基督為了人的救
去過貧窮的生活
He gave up the most comfortable life
for the sake of the Lord
He wanted to live a life of a poor man
to the Lord
and the way of the Lord
search the Lord
a way of denial
由富足變貧窮的路
that a rich man become poor
結果他有熟齡的父親
And because of that
he has spiritual richness
我們再看
很驚訝不驚訝
我們的主
Our Lord
取了奴僕的形象
He took the form of a servant
和我們交換
and extended with us
所以我們這些原來做奴僕的人
得以自由
So that we who once lived in the past
now become free
在基督的那個完全的自由
There is a whole true freedom in Christ indeed
我們的兒女的那個榮耀的自由
There is a glorious freedom
of the children of God
因為他們交換
Because Christ exchanged with us
所以我們得到這樣的奇妙的自由
That's why we have this marvelous
marvelous freedom
我相信在宣教的這個歷史裡
I believe that in the mission history
我們很多人知道的一個
最感動人的事情
Many people knew about this thing
那就是in West Indies
有人把自己出賣做奴隸
為了要到奴隸中間傳福音
That people who sell themselves to become slaves
so they can go to the land of slaves
and to preach the gospel
真是世上不配有的人
It is some people
the world is not worthy to have
但是是歷史
But then it's the history
是事實
It's a fact
基督的愛的濟勵
That the love of Christ constrained them
我們衝突得了這個自由以後
After receiving this freedom from Christ
我們再次像基督一樣
放下這個自由的權
Once more we want to deny
this freedom and this right
中國人做宣教士還是很難很難
For Chinese to become a mission
is difficult, difficult
大家同意不同意
Do you agree with me?
中國人走上拆船
做宣教士路的人
還是比例很小
And the proportion of those Chinese
who become missionaries
is still very low
很難放下
Because it's very difficult for them to give up
原來什麼都沒有的
容易放下
因為放下的很少
Well when you have nothing
it's easy for you to deny
because you have not much to deny
原來已經有了不少的
這個權力地位
But when you have quite a lot of position
and also wealth
所以說放下
And you want to deny it?
很容易
It's not easy
不能夠踏上這一步
You cannot take the first step
中國的基督徒
Chinese Christians
很愛主
Love the Lord very much
在愛主的感情上
不亞於歐美的弟兄妹
Emotionally they are not second to the Europeans
但是在真的擺上這件事上
我們還有很遠的
很長的一條路要走
But in this true act of giving up
we still have a long, long way to go
真的中國人不可能做宣教士嗎?
Is it true that Chinese cannot become a missionary?
我不相信
I do not believe
如果世子家的愛感動了歐美
那些享受那麼多的人做宣教士
If the love of the cross can conceive so many westerners
so they become missionaries
為什麼中國人不會?
Why not Chinese?
Yes we can
我相信
I believe
繼續有人中國的弟兄妹走上宣教士的路
There will be Chinese Christians who will take the way of the missionaries
我們看見我們的主
他純心卑微
We see that our Lord was willing to degrade himself
自己卑微
He degraded himself
我們的主
他降到最卑微的地步
Our Lord humbled himself to the lowest point
他生在麻草裡
He was born a ninja
一個神的兒子生在麻草裡
The son of God born in a stable
神的選擇
It is the election of God
也是主自己的選擇
And so his own choice
所以我生在麻草裡
If I was born to be born in a stable
我會保持我人生中最高的秘密
什麼人也不給他知道
Oh I keep it a secret
I don't disclose to anybody
如果有人知道我生在麻草裡
真是面上光
It is a shame for people to know that I am born in such a lowly place
那不是人生的地方
But not a place for men to be born
那是牲畜的地方
That is a place of the animals
神的選擇
By the choice of God
基督的選擇
No coincidence
Glorious Christ
生在麻草裡
Was born in a manger
不是人下人
Not a man below man
那是牲畜到了牲口的水平上
But not to the level of the animal's life
我們不能了解
We cannot understand
我們一看見那個圖畫
When you see the picture
有三位博士
Three wise men
跪在這個麻草裡面的聖嬰前
Kneeling before the baby of the manger
我們了解
最尊貴的人
The most glorious
最寶貴的禮物
The most precious gift
獻給這個麻草裡面的嬰兒
Dedicated to this baby in the manger
今天我們把他舉得至高
Do they want to leave him behind?
He is the Lord
He is the King of kings
我們這樣做的時候
When you do such
我們心裡很喜樂
In the heart is full with joy
我們說
從我讓你退
We say Lord you are worthy
因為你為我降賢
Because you humble yourself for my sake
無以復加的榮耀
A lordness that cannot be lowered anymore
從我我要將你舉起
無以復加的至高
Lord I want to lift you high
Handsome all highness
今天我們領受這段經文
Today as we receive this passage
求主給我們一個信誌
Pray that God give us a mind
與主同死
To die with him
跟隨基督
To follow Christ
到底
To the end
And the end
In detail
Let's pray
我們要用一段時間來默想
Want to have a time of meditation
我相信這七節聖經
不需要我再提什麼要點了
I truly believe that I don't have to narrow
any more of the important points of this Bible
我們就八六節到第十一節
拿來做默想
When we meditate upon verses 5 to 11
我們在默想的時候
求聖靈來向我們說話
As you meditate
want to pray that the Holy Spirit will speak to us
我們開始默想
Begin to meditate upon these verses
(默想)
我們一起來禱告
Let us pray together
(默想)
Bend and adore
The Lord of grace
我們將我們的眼睛固定
在你和你的十字架上
Want to fix our eyes upon you
and on the cross
當我們這樣做默的時候
As we fix our eyes
我們真心願意像使徒保羅一樣說
We want to be like Paul saying
我定了主義
Where I fix my mind
不知道別的
只知道基督和他定十字架
Not knowing anything but only Christ
and Christ who is on the cross
(默想)
當我們需要背十字架的時候
求你讓我們不退縮
(默想)
所以你讓我們計算代價
然後不計代價的去跟從你
(默想)
所以我們多少時候何等的懺悔
比如說我們發現我們的背上沒有十字架
(默想)
所以我們不知不覺求自己的地位榮耀
所以我們要求你接近我們
(默想)
用你的愛來接近我們
或者用你的保持來接近
(默想)
用你的愛來接近
讓剩下的就是愛
(默想)
所以求你在我們的裡面居所謂
我們願意攻擊你的時候自己降低
(默想)
所以我們放著我們有這樣的一個心智
為自己不求什麼為主求一切
(默想)
所以我們為自己常常求的太多
我們常常抓住我們的權利
(默想)
我們放下一點的時候
我們覺得付了太大的代價
(默想)
所以我但願今天你自己充滿我們的眼淚
我們的心靈
(默想)
今天讓不見一人去見耶穌
所以我願意在我們心中居所謂
(默想)
在我們的教會中居所謂
在我們的生活和侍奉中居所謂
(默想)
所以我幫助我們
願意讓我們的一切與主同定
(默想)
讓我們的肉體
我們的自我
(默想)
這個世界
都釘在十字架上
(默想)
所以我感謝你
為我們釘十字架
(默想)
感恩之餘
我們願意與你同釘十字架
(默想)
我們再一次把釘十字架
十字架暴露的信息
放在每一個人的心中
(默想)
我向耶穌基督領導
我們祈求耶穌基督
(默想)